<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://marymoto.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://marymoto.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-01-19T21:26:09+00:00</updated><id>https://marymoto.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Advantages, Specialization, and Opportunity Costs</title><link href="https://marymoto.github.io/blog/2024/muddy-points-module-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advantages, Specialization, and Opportunity Costs"/><published>2024-01-18T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-18T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://marymoto.github.io/blog/2024/muddy-points-module-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marymoto.github.io/blog/2024/muddy-points-module-1/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="i-hear-you-folks">I hear you, folks.</h2> <p>This stuff can be <em>very</em> confusing. So, here is some (hopefully) helpful supplemental material. This will not be an adequate substitute for our textbook or lectures, but more a complementary good [we’ll get more to this topic at a later point :smiley:].</p> <h2 id="key-definitions">Key Definitions:</h2> <h5 id="absolute-advantage"><strong>Absolute advantage</strong></h5> <p><strong>CORE’s definition</strong>: “A person or country has absolute advantage in the production of a good if the inputs it uses to produce this good are less than in some other person or country”</p> <h5 id="opportunity-cost"><strong>Opportunity cost</strong></h5> <p><strong>CORE’s definition</strong>: “When taking an action implies forgoing the next best alternative action, the opportunity cost is the net benefit of the forgone alternative”</p> <h5 id="comparative-advantage"><strong>Comparative advantage</strong></h5> <p><strong>CORE’s definition</strong>: “A person or country has comparative advantage in the production of a particular good, if the cost of producing an addition unit of the good relative to the cost of producing another good is lower than another person or country’s cost to produce the same two goods”</p> <h5 id="specialization"><strong>Specialization</strong></h5> <p><strong>CORE’s definition</strong>: “Specialization takes place when a country or some other entity produces a more narrow range of goods and services than it consumes, acquiring the goods and services it does not produce by trade”</p> <h2 id="my-3-step-system--example-problems">My 3 Step System + Example Problems</h2> <h5 id="solve-for-absolute-advantages-and-write-them-down">Solve for <strong>absolute advantage(s)</strong> and write them down</h5> <h5 id="look-for-the-comparative-advantages-and-make-a-new-table">Look for the <strong>comparative advantages</strong> and make a new table</h5> <h5 id="analyze-simplified-table-to-determine-opportunity-costs-of-different-actions">Analyze simplified table to determine <strong>opportunity costs</strong> of different actions</h5> <h5 id="bonus-tip-when-in-doubt-relate-back-to-what-you-know">BONUS TIP: When in doubt, relate back to what you know</h5> <ul> <li>What are you and your bestie good at/less good at?</li> <li>Real life examples (real countries, friends, athletes, etc.) <br/></li> </ul> <h2 id="our-motivating-example-a-tale-of-two-study-groups">Our Motivating Example: A Tale of Two Study Groups</h2> <h3 id="when-advantages-align-artha-and-bianca">When Advantages Align: Artha and Bianca</h3> <p>Two friends, <em>Artha</em> and <em>Bianca</em> are deciding how to get all their finals review work done given their busy schedules. Since finals week is all about <strong>scarcity</strong>, they decide to divide and conquer to maximize their efficiency and grades! They both have unique strengths for Spanish and Finance, and are able to work together on their final projects for the two classes. The girls relative strengths for these two subjects are as described in the table below:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th style="text-align: center">Spanish Paper</th> <th style="text-align: center">Finance Presentation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Artha</td> <td style="text-align: center">95</td> <td style="text-align: center">80</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Bianca</td> <td style="text-align: center">80</td> <td style="text-align: center">95</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <p>The table can be read such that if Artha spends <strong>100%</strong> of her available time during finals week working on their Spanish paper, the girls’ expected final grade in Spanish is a 95% (top left cell) and so on. Let’s walk through my 3 steps together to figure out how the girls should split their efforts to maximize their grades!</p> <h5 id="step-one-solve-for-absolute-advantages-and-write-them-down"><strong>STEP ONE:</strong> Solve for absolute advantage(s) and write them down.</h5> <ul> <li>In Spanish (left column), Artha has the <strong>absolute advantage</strong> (95% &gt; 80%)</li> <li>In Finance (right column), Bianca has the <strong>absolute advantage</strong> (95% &gt; 80%) <blockquote> <p>:bulb: <strong>PRO TIP:</strong> When this is the case where each entity has a different absolute advantage, we can actually skip the rest of the steps! Artha will spend her time on the Spanish paper, and Bianca will spend hers on the Finance presentation, and this maximizes both of the girls’ final grades! How cool, right? When you are short on time or feel really confident with this topic, feel free to charge forth wothout going through these other steps once you come to this realization. If you are already at this point, skip ahead to the Cyril and Demir example!</p> </blockquote> </li> </ul> <h5 id="step-two-look-for-the-comparative-advantages-and-make-a-new-table"><strong>STEP TWO:</strong> Look for the comparative advantages and make a new table</h5> <p>This is the one and only math-y step, I promise! We are now going to calculate their relative outputs of Spanish and Finance points to one another.</p> <ul> <li>For <strong>Spanish</strong>: <ul> <li>Artha earns (95/80) = 1.19 relative to Bianca</li> <li>Bianca earns (80/95) = 0.84 relative to Artha</li> </ul> </li> <li>For <strong>Finance</strong>: <ul> <li>Artha earns (80/95) = 0.84 relative to Bianca</li> <li>Bianca earns (95/80) = 1.19 relative to Artha <br/></li> </ul> </li> </ul> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th style="text-align: center">Spanish Paper</th> <th style="text-align: center">Finance Presentation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Artha</td> <td style="text-align: center">1.19x</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.84x</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Bianca</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.84x</td> <td style="text-align: center">1.19x</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <p>Once you do this, you will have something like the table above. This table will make it easier for us to visually compare opportunity cost, comparative advantage, and how to best specialize given the scarcity Artha and Bianca face!</p> <h5 id="step-three-analyze-new-table-to-determine-opportunity-costs-of-different-actions"><strong>STEP THREE:</strong> Analyze new table to determine opportunity costs of different actions</h5> <p>We read these tables from LEFT to RIGHT. Let’s start with Artha</p> <ul> <li>Artha: Can earn 1.19x the points towards their Spanish paper as Bianca, and earns 0.84x the points towards Finance as Bianca <ul> <li>Since 1.19 &gt; 0.84, Artha has a comparative advantage in Spanish</li> </ul> </li> <li>Bianca: Earns 0.84x the points towards Spanish as Artha and 1.19x the points towards Finance as Artha <ul> <li>Since 1.19 &gt; 0.84, Bianca has a comparative advantage in Finance <br/></li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h3 id="are-two-heads-always-better-cyril-and-demir">Are Two Heads Always Better? Cyril and Demir</h3> <p>In the above example, this all seems very straightforward. Artha knows her conditional perfect tense like the back of her hand? Have her run with Spanish! Bianca is a forecasting and valuation wizard? Okay then, get out of her way! But, what about when a group is less equally matched in their abilities, you may be wondering:</p> <h6 id="should-we-still-specialize-when-one-entity-has-an-absolute-advantage-in-both-goods"><strong>Should we still specialize when one entity has an absolute advantage in both goods?</strong></h6> <p>Well, across campus in a different library we have another study group, <em>Cyril</em> and <em>Demir</em>, who have the following advantage table:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th style="text-align: center">Spanish Paper</th> <th style="text-align: center">Finance Presentation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Cyril</td> <td style="text-align: center">90</td> <td style="text-align: center">95</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Demir</td> <td style="text-align: center">85</td> <td style="text-align: center">80</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <h5 id="step-one-solve-for-absolute-advantages"><strong>STEP ONE:</strong> Solve for absolute advantage(s)</h5> <p>Unlike with Artha and Bianca above, you may notice here that in both Spanish and Finance, Cyril has an absolute advantage compared to Demir!</p> <ul> <li>If Cyril spends 100% of his available time on… <ul> <li>Finance, their joint expected grade is a 95%</li> <li>Spanish, their joint expected grade is a 90%</li> </ul> </li> <li>If Demir spends 100% of his available time on… <ul> <li>Finance, their joint expected grade is a 80%</li> <li>Spanish, their joint expected grade is a 85%</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>In both cases, Cyril’s expected output (final grade) given his input (study time) is higher than Demir’s. So, what happens now? This is where really understanding comparative advantage and opportunity cost comes in!</p> <h5 id="step-two-look-for-the-comparative-advantages-and-make-a-new-table-1"><strong>STEP TWO:</strong> Look for the comparative advantages and make a new table</h5> <ul> <li>For <strong>Spanish</strong>: <ul> <li>Cyril earns (90/85) = 1.06 relative to Demir</li> <li>Demir earns (85/90) = 0.94 relative to Cyril</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Now, we do the same thing for their Finance scores</p> <ul> <li>For <strong>Finance</strong>: <ul> <li>Cyril earns (95/80) = 1.19 relative to Demir</li> <li>Demir earns (80/95) = 0.84 relative to Cyril <br/></li> </ul> </li> </ul> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: center"> </th> <th style="text-align: center">Spanish Paper</th> <th style="text-align: center">Finance Presentation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Cyril</td> <td style="text-align: center">1.06x</td> <td style="text-align: center">1.19x</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: center">Demir</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.94x</td> <td style="text-align: center">0.84x</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <h5 id="step-three-analyze-new-table-to-determine-opportunity-costs-of-different-actions-1"><strong>STEP THREE:</strong> Analyze new table to determine opportunity costs of different actions</h5> <ul> <li>Cyril: Has a comparative advantage on the Finance Presentation <ul> <li>Cyril’s opportunity cost: the points on the Spanish paper he can earn for the team with the same amount of time he spends on Finance (1.19 &gt; 1.06)</li> </ul> </li> <li>Demir: Has a comparative advantage on the Spanish Paper <ul> <li>Demir’s opportunity cost: the points on the Finance presentation he would earn with the time he instead dedicates to the Spanish paper (0.94 &gt; 0.84)</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h2 id="wrapping-it-up-connecting-some-dots">Wrapping it up: Connecting Some Dots</h2> <p>Thanks to <strong>scarcity</strong> of resources (including time, land, money, labor), we cannot do everything all of the time! So, we need to find ways to efficiently divide tasks –&gt; <strong>specialization</strong>!</p> <p><br/> <strong>What should we specialize in?</strong></p> <p>Well, probably something we are good at, or have an <strong>advantage</strong> in… There are <strong>two types</strong> of advantages: absolute and comparative</p> <ul> <li><strong>Absolute advantage</strong> <ul> <li>One entity can have absolute advantage in BOTH goods being compared</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Comparative advantage</strong> <ul> <li>Each entity will have a comparative advantage in ONE of the goods being compared</li> <li>Why? Comparative advantage is about your next best alternative (or forgone conclusion) in order to product that good… there’s a word for this</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Opportunity cost</strong>: the entity with the lower opportunity cost of production of a good has the comparative advantage!</li> </ul> <p><strong>But MARY!</strong></p> <ul> <li>What about <em>my</em> preferences? Don’t they matter at all here?</li> <li>How do I decide how much of my time to spend study versus doing other things?</li> </ul> <p>GREAT questions, hypothetical student! Until next time…</p> <p>– Professor Mary –</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching"/><category term="macro"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Principles of Marco Supplemental Materials for 2023 - 2024]]></summary></entry></feed>